Guide to the Evaporated Milk Association Collection, 1924-1934 RL.00373
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Evaporated Milk Association collection
1924-1934
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Evaporated Milk Association
RL.00373
0.6 Linear Feet
The Evaporated Milk Association, organized by manufacturers in 1923, issued free publications promoting the use of evaporated milk throughout the United States. This collection consists of publications with recipes, scientific studies, and stories encouraging the consumption of canned evaporated milk. These pamphlets and booklets were donated to Duke University Libraries in the 1930s by the Evaporated Milk Association.
86 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Evaporated Milk Association Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer from Perkins Library in 2009. The collection was originally donated between 1929 and 1934.
Historical Note
Evaporated milk was developed over the course of the 19th century to address the need of armed forces in Europe to preserve food for long periods of time. Initially, milk was boiled and reduced, bottled with sugar, and then boiled again to create a seal. By the end of the American Civil War, sweetened condensed milk had grown in popularity, and its success encouraged inventors John B. Meyenberg and Louis Latzer to form the first unsweetened evaporated milk plant in Highland, Illinois. Meyenberg received an 1884 U.S. patent covering the process of sterilizing by steam under pressure. In 1885, evaporated milk was manufactured commercially for the first time.
The Spanish-American War further popularized evaporated milk as a sterile and transportable means of feeding troops. The introduction of homogenization in 1909 and continuous sterilization in 1922 led to increased consumption by the general public, and the milk was widely used to feed American troops during World War I.
The Evaporated Milk Association was organized by manufacturers in 1923, seeking to promote and encourage the consumption of evaporated milk, and also to research additional uses for the product. In the following years, recipes were developed and disseminated by the EMA through women's magazines, home economics professors, newspapers, and EMA pamphlets such as those sent to Duke Libraries. Furthermore, the Association sponsored numerous clinical studies (and reprinted independent studies) that encouraged the use of evaporated milk for infant feeding. This promotion was steadily expanded through the 1930s with an experimental kitchen, movies, educational outreach, and additional publications. The EMA sought to convince consumers that evaporated milk was a cost-effective, healthy, and safe product for budget-conscious family.
The Evaporated Milk Association continued to lobby and promote the industry throughout World War II and during the post-war period. It merged with the American Dairy Products Institute in 1987.
Collection Overview
This collection originally arrived at Perkins Library as three binders of promotional materials from the Evaporated Milk Association. The materials have been transferred to Rubenstein Library and are no longer in binders.
The materials include both pamphlets and booklets covering a wide range of themes -- all relating to evaporated milk and targeting potential consumers. Topics include: recipes, both for regular cooking, desserts, and for preparing large quantities of food; studies and articles promoting infant feeding using evaporated milk; plays and activities for children centering on the emergency delivery of evaporated milk rations (among other supplies) to isolated areas; cost breakdowns of evaporated milk versus fresh milk, aimed at budget-conscious families; cartoons detailing the delicious flavor of evaporated milk; reprints of medical or scientific journal articles discussing evaporated milk's consumption in impoverished or malnourished communities, or by populations with various diseases; and articles about the history of evaporated milk, its manufacturing process, and general information about evaporated milk as a product. All of these pamphlets date from the pre-World War II period and are aimed at American readers.
The booklets and pamphlets have been kept in the order in which they were arranged in the binders. Dates are included when known.
Evaporated milk; Grocery shopping; Infants -- Nutrition; Home economics -- United States -- History; Recipes; Cookery; Vitamin D in human nutrition -- History; Breastfeeding -- United States -- History; Canned foods; Evaporated Milk Association; Evaporated Milk Association; Milk in human nutrition
- Pamphlets and Booklets, 1924-1934, 1 box
  - Binder 1, Folder 1 (Box 1)
    - Milk Drinks with the Better Richness, undated (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk: What it is, Why it is, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Food Fit for Camping Appetites, 1927 (Box 1)
    - Publications that may be obtained free through the Evaporated Milk Association, undated (Box 1)
    - 20 New Ice Cream Formulae, undated (Box 1)
    - A Quart of Milk a Day, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Safety and Simplicity in Infant Feeding, 1928 (Box 1)
    - From Cow...to Consumer, 1928 (Box 1)
    - The Story of Evaporated Milk, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Eating for Efficiency, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Binder 1, Folder 2
    - The Patient and the Diet, 1928 (Box 1)
    - The Use of Unsweetened Evaporated Milk in Therapeutic Diets (reprint), 1928 (Box 1)
    - A Comparison of Evaporated Milk with Pasteurized Milk as a Source of Calcium, Phosphorus, and Nitrogen (reprint), 1927 (Box 1)
    - Textures of Ice Creams as Influenced by Some Constituents (reprint), 1928 (Box 1)
    - The Use of Unsweetened Evaporated Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1927 (Box 1)
    - The Preparation of Acidophilus Milk (reprint), 1928 (Box 1)
    - The Baby's Milk (reprint), 1928 (Box 1)
    - Scientific References Pointing to the High Nutritive Value of Evaporated Milk (reprint), undated (Box 1)
    - Scientific References Pointing to the High Nutritive Value of Evaporated Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), undated (Box 1)
  - Binder 2, Folder 1
    - Prescription booklet with infant formula chart, undated (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk: Pure Cow's Milk for Every Milk Use (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - What Evaporated Milk Offers the Dentist (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - What to Make with Red Cross Flour (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - Supplementary Mid-Morning Feeding of Rural School Children (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - More Food for Your Money (reprint), undated (Box 1)
    - Economies in Food: Quantity Recipes Using Evaporated Milk, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Why Evaporated Milk Makes Good Food Better, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Celiac Disease Treated from the Standpoint of Vitamin Deficiency (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - The Use of Evaporated Milk in Digestive Disorders, Particularly Peptic Ulcer (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
  - Binder 2, Folder 2
    - A Comparative Study of the Use of Unsweetened Evaporated Milk and Bottled Cow's Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk Drinks, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Safe and Unsafe Economy (reprint), undated (Box 1)
    - The Use of Evaporated Milk in Quantity Cooking (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - Proteins, Minerals and Vitamins of Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - A Comparison of the Nutritional and Growth Values of Certain Infant Foods (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - Growth and Retentions of Calcium, Phosphorus and Nitrogen of Infants Fed Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - A Science Project, undated (Box 1)
    - A Housewife Looks at the Committee on Foods (reprint), 1934 (Box 1)
    - The Airplane Rescue: A Play for Elementary Grades, undated (Box 1)
    - The Laughing Moon: A Play for Junior and Senior High School, and Parent Groups, undated (Box 1)
  - Binder 3, Folder 1
    - The Advantages of Evaporated Milk in Allergy and Infant Feeding (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - The Adventures of Eva, Pora, and Ted, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk Around the World (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk for Health and Protection, 1932 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk in Tropical West Africa, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Feeding a Family at Low Cost, 1932 (Box 1)
    - The Food Value of Frozen Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Frozen Foods: The Automatic Way, 1931 (Box 1)
    - The History of Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - The Hot School Lunch: A Report of Programs Conducted by Fifty-seven Teachers in Rural Schools (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Ice-Frozen Desserts: Ice Creams, Sherbets, and Frozen Custards, 1932 (Box 1)
    - The Indispensable Food (reprint), 1930 (Box 1)
    - Infant Feeding with Unsweetened Evaporated Milk, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Infantile Diarrhea (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
  - Binder 3, Folder 2
    - Lemon Juice Evaporated Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Low Fat High Starch Evaporated Milk Feeding for the Marasmic Baby (reprint), 1931 (Box 1)
    - Milk: Spend Less, Have More by using Evaporated Milk, undated (Box 1)
    - Milk for Better Meals, 1932 (Box 1)
    - Milk for Drinking as You Like It, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Modern Milk: The Story of Evaporated Milk, 1933 (Box 1)
    - More Milk, Smaller Bills, 1932 (Box 1)
    - New Facts about Baby Feeding (reprint), undated (Box 1)
    - Nutritive Value of Evaporated Milk, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Overcoming Food Dislikes: A Study with Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1929 (Box 1)
    - Planning Lunches for School Children, 1931 (Box 1)
    - Quantity Recipes for Serving 25-50, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Binder 3, Folder 3
    - Recent Developments in the Use of Evaporated Milk in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1930 (Box 1)
    - The Relative Quantities of the Heat-Stable and Heat-Labile Fractions of Vitamin B in Raw and Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - A Safer World for Babies, 1931 (Box 1)
    - A Simple, Inexpensive Stock Formula for Young Infants (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Some Facts about Evaporated Milk and Dairy Products, 1932 (Box 1)
    - Some Foods for Children, 1932 (Box 1)
    - The Sweet Taste of Safety That Comes from the Heating of Milk, undated (Box 1)
    - The Treatment of Peptic Ulcers with an Evaporated Milk Diet (reprint), 1933 (Box 1)
    - A Bacteriological Investigation of Evaporated Milk (reprint), 1931 (Box 1)
    - A Comparison of the Vitamin G Values of Pasteurized Milk, Evaporated Milk, and Eggs (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - A Comparative Study of Infant Foods (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Concentrated Milk in the Days of Napoleon, undated (Box 1)
    - Effect of Evaporated Milk on the Incidence of Rickets in Infants (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Milk Made Candies, 1931 (Box 1)
    - The Care of Premature Infants (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Essentials in Infant Feeding (reprint), 1931 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated Milk: The Story of Its Development from 1810 to 1932 (reprint), 1932 (Box 1)
    - Evaporated and Condensed Milk from the Chemical and Nutritional Point of View (reprint), 1930 (Box 1)
    - The White Rat of Hawkins Hall, 1932 (Box 1)